A Guide to the Garnett Ryland Essex County Records, 1685-1796
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Garnett Ryland Essex County Records, 1685-1796
The Library of Virginia
23438
6 leaves and 40 pages
Garnett Ryland
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 22 December 1949, of Garnett Ryland.
Biographical Information
Garnett Ryland was born 17 December 1870 in King and Queen County, Virginia, to Dr. Charles Hill Ryland (1836-1914) and Alice Marion Garnett Ryland (1846-1931). Ryland's father, Dr. Ryland, served as treasurer and librarian for Richmond College, and his great-uncle, Dr. Robert Ryland (1805-1899) was the school's first president. Garnett Ryland received his M.A. in chemistry from Richmond College in 1892 and his doctorate from Johns Hopkins. He taught at the University of Maine, at Converse College in South Carolina, and at Georgetown College in Kentucky, before returning to the University of Richmond in 1917, where he taught chemistry until 1945. After his retirement, he served as secretery of the Virginia Baptist Historical Society. Ryland married Lewella Payne (1887-1980) of Scott County, Kentucky, 21 December 1909. He died 2 February 1962 in Richmond.
Scope and Content
Essex County, Virginia, records, 1685-1796, collected by Garnett Ryland (1870-1962) of King and Queen County and Richmond, Virginia, consisting of bonds, 1685-1774, recorded in (Old) Rappahannock and Essex Counties, Virginia; wills, 1715-1796, of John Fargeson, James Jameson, Thomas Garnett, Daniel Gaines, John Webb, John Farguson, John Garnett, Joseph Ryland, and Nathaniel Fogg, all of Essex County; inventories, orders, accounts of sales, and divisions, 1744-1773, of decedents' estates in Essex County; a power of attorney, 16 May 1720, of Margaret Jameson to Samuel Stalard, both of Essex County; a deed, 5 March 1772, for her estate rights from Mary Garnett to Reuben Garnett, both of Essex County; a deed, 16 November 1778, for 240 acres in Essex County from Reuben and Mary Garnett and his wife Mary to Hancock Lee; and a marriage agreement, 23 October 1778, between Richard Cheek of King and Queen County, Virginia, and Elizabeth Ryland of Essex County.
Contents List
- Bond, recorded 12 May and 27 May 1685, for William Slaughter as high sheriff of [Old] Rappahannock County, Virginia.
- Will, dated 10 May 1715 and recorded 19 March 1717, of John Fargeson of Essex County.
- Bond, recorded 19 March 1717/1718, of Anne Fargeson, John Fargeson, and James Fargeson, all of Essex County.
- Power of attorney, dated 16 May 1720 and recorded 17 May 1720, of Margaret Jameson to Samuel Stalard, both of Essex County.
- Will, dated 19 April 1736 and recorded 17 November 1736, of James Jameson of Essex County.
- Will, dated 9 December 1733 and recorded 20 December 1743, of Thomas Garnett of Essex County.
- Inventory, recorded 19 June 1744, of the estate of Thomas Garnett by Elizabeth Garnett of Essex County.
- Order, 15 May 1753, for Robert Brooke, et. al., to appraise the estate of Nathaniel Fogg.
- Inventory, recorded 19 June 1753, of the estate of Nathaniel Fogg by Cornelius Sale, Nicholas Faulconer, and John Sale, all of Essex County (for Fogg's will, see last item in list).
- Will, dated 21 April 1757 and recorded 19 July 1757, of Daniel Gaines of Essex County.
- Will, dated 14 March 1767 and recorded 15 June 1767, of John Webb of Essex County.
- Will, dated 22 April 1769 and recorded 16 April 1770, of John Farguson of Essex County.
- Will, dated 6 January 1772 and recorded 16 March 1772, of John Garnett of Essex County.
- Deed, dated 5 March 1772 and recorded 20 April 1772, for her estate rights from Mary Garnett to her son Reuben Garnett, both of Essex County.
- Inventory, recorded 20 April 1772, of the estate of John Garnett by John Sale, Richard Noelly, and John Taylor, all of Essex County.
- Account of sales, 20 April 1772, of the estate of John Garnett by Reuben Garnett of Essex County.
- Will, dated 29 November 1771 and recorded 21 September 1772, of Joseph Ryland of Essex County.
- Bond, recorded 16 November 1772, of Samuel Peachey, James Edmondson, and James Webb, all of Essex County.
- Division, recorded 20 September 1773, of the estate of Joseph Ryland by Samuel Allen, James Booker, and Thomas Wood.
- Bond, recorded 21 March 1774, of Samuel Peachey and William Smith.
- Deed, dated and recorded 16 November 1778, for 240 acres in Essex County from Reuben Garnett and his wife Mary to Hancock Lee.
- Marriage agreement, dated 23 October 1778 and recorded 18 October 1779, between Richard Cheek of King and Queen County, Virginia, and Elizabeth Ryland of Essex County.
- Will, dated 10 December 1752, recorded 17 May 1753, and re-recorded January 1796, of Nathaniel Fogg of Essex County.